Scientist in Residence Program Records
University of Houston-Clear Lake Archives & Special Collections
The Scientist in Residence Program Records
2005-2013
Pastrana, Ronald
2011-0013
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
University of Houston-Clear Lake Archives & Special Collections
Scientist in Residence Program Records covers the collection and donations of educational materials by Dr. Ronald Pastrana to Mill Road Intermediate School from 2006-2008.
Biographical Sketch
Dr. Ronald Pastrana, a retired NASA scientist, first initiated the Scientist in Residence Program at Mill Road Intermediate School in 2006 as a two-day enrichment program for fourth graders. In 2008, Dr. Pastrana moved the program to first and fourth graders at Chancellor Livingston Elementary School, where it subsequently grew into an all-grades week-long event augmenting their standard science curriculum.
The program provides students with background information and hands-on experiences to discuss lunar geology, Earth and Life Sciences, as well as other topics related to the U.S. Space Program. The impact of the program on the student's interests may be clearly seen through the many samples of student essay letters, images, and research papers submitted by following the program.
Materials were donated to the UHCL Archives with the hopes that Education majors would be interested in researching programs utilizing primary documents on space science in elementary schools.
The donated materials were used by UHCL Archives for a Neumann Library exhibit during Fall 2010, as part of the 2009 Lunar Landing anniversary exhibit and 2010 Archives Month exhibit at the Clear Lake City-County Freeman Branch Library exhibit.
Scope and Contents Note
When this program began at Livingston Chancellor Elementary School in 2008, Dr. Ron Pastrana donated various examples of student artwork and essay letters for the UHCL Archives. These items were housed in the UHCL Archives Vertical File under the term Scientist in Residence Program (Rhinebeck, NY) by the year. Dr. Pastrana annually contributed student research essays, images, artwork, thank you letters, and program overview. These items were formally processed out of the Vertical File and into the Scientist in Residence Program Records after the 2011 donation and also includes addenda up to 2013.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into seven series based on chronology:
Series I: 2005
Series II: 2006
Series III: 2008
Series IV: 2009
Series V: 2010
Series VI: 2011
Series VII: 2013
Access Restrictions
Unrestricted
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Pastrana, Ronald
Subjects (Organizations)
Chancellor Livingston Elementary School
Subjects
Education--Space Science
Places
Rhinebeck (N.Y.)
Acquisition Information
Materials donated annually in the late summer by Dr. Ronald Pastrana - latest addenda donated July 2014
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: 2005
  - Faith and Space Programs, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: 2006
  - Program Overview - Mill Road School, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Images, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Student Response Essay Letters, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series III: 2008
  - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Images, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Student Artwork, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Student Response Essay Letters, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series IV: 2009
  - Correspondence, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Program Overview - Chancellor Livingston Elementary School, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - First Grade Project, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Student Response Essay Letters, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Student Response Letters and Images, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Student Artwork, 2009 (Folder OS - flat file)
- Series V: 2010
  - Correspondence (includes Thank You Letters), 2010 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Program Overview, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Images, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - First Grade Project, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Student Response Letters and Images (Kindergarten & 5th grade), 2010 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Student Response Letters and Images (4th grade), 2010 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Student Research Essays, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Student Artwork (Folder OS-flat file)
- Series VI: 2011
  - Correspondence, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Program Overview - Chancellor Livingston Elementary School, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - First Grade Project, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Student Response Letters and Images, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Student Research Essays, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
- Series VII: 2013
  - Program Overview - Chancellor Livingston Elementary School, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Student Letters and Photographs (Kindergarten-5th Grade), 2013 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student Essays and Reports (4th and 5th Grade), 2013 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Student Projects (1st and 2nd Grade), 2013 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Student Projects (3rd Grade), 2013 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Student Packet (objects include NASA photographs, cards, and other mementos), 2013 (Box 3, Folder 3)